Phillip: There are many advantages to working
in teams but there are also disadvantages.
Being aware of both of these, can make
it easier for you to consider, how to
approach different projects and tasks.
Maddy: In a team leadership context, knowing
the disadvantages you tend to find in
teams, will help you mitigate their effects.
And knowing the advantages will
help you act to reinforce them.
So, let’s start by looking at the Advantages
Phillip: Productivity – Teams tend to
be more productive than individuals.
This is because a team has a
wide pool of individual talents,
experience, and knowledge to draw from.
And with more pairs of hands, more work
can get done in a shorter amount of time,
if tasks are appropriately allocated.
Maddy: Ideas – In a team, ideas should
be shared frequently and openly.
This not only allows everyone to have their
say, but it also exposes them to ideas
they might not otherwise have considered.
Phillip: Belonging – In a team, you’re
not just one individual on your own,
you are part of a group of people
working together, for the same goal.
This can create a powerful sense of belonging,
which is good for people’s wellbeing and morale.
Maddy: Mentorship – Teams give people
access to mentors who can support and
guide them on their career pathway.
This can be official or unofficial.
Phillip: Networking and relationships –In a team,
you’re dealing with a wider group of people, this
increases your professional and social circle.
This can also lead to unexpected
development opportunities, you might
not otherwise have encountered.
Maddy: So, now let’s look at the Disadvantages
Loss of individuality – For a team
to function properly, everyone
needs to put the team’s needs first.
What this means in practice can be variable, but
it can result in some team members feeling like
they’ve lost their autonomy and individuality,
by not being able to prioritise themselves,
their ambitions, their desires, and their ideas.
Phillip: Groupthink – Teams need to have
consensus to function and that can sometimes
mean teams tend towards groupthink.
That’s a situation where new ideas don’t get a
hearing because “That’s not how we do things”.
In a situation like that, the team has
become too inward looking and conservative.
Maddy: Cliques – Because teams often
become quite tightknit, this can leave
people not in the team, feeling left out.
The team may even come to think of
itself as superior to “outsiders”, and
sometimes cliques can form within the team,
making some team members feel alienated.
Phillip: Competition with other teams
– There’s nothing wrong with a bit of healthy
competition between teams in a workplace,
in fact, workplaces often encourage it.
But it can go too far, and lead to
teams prioritising themselves, over the
strategic goals of the organisation.
Maddy: Inequality in the team – although
everyone in an effective team should
be collaborating and working together,
inevitable situations will arise where some
people are given more to do than others.
This can be for a lot of reasons such as
scheduling, professional experience, and so on.
It can produce problems if some members
of the team start to perceive this as
favouritism or that their willingness
to work is being taken advantage of.
Phillip: On the whole teams have very strong
advantages, and will often outperform less
closely organised groups, but we can’t ignore
the disadvantages that are inherent in teams.
But we shouldn’t consider these disadvantages
as “failures” of teams, they inevitably
occur every now and again, because they
are totally reflective of human nature.
What is important though, is that we are
realistic in our understanding of the
problems, that even the most effective
teams will eventually have to deal with.